Finding aid of Rick Mechtly cinema clippings collection Coll2012.162
ONE National Gay Lesbian Archives, USC Libraries, University of Southern California
Rick Mechtly Cinema Clippings Collection
1966-2011
Coll2012.162
ONE National Gay Lesbian Archives, USC Libraries, University of Southern California
3.8 linear feet. [3 records boxes]
Clippings of articles, columns, and reviews regarding LGBT actors, motion pictures, and film festivals. The files were culled from a variety of mainstream and LBGT magazines and newspapers, 1966-2011. Mechtley began collecting LGBT film clippings in the 1970s. Vito Russo introduced Metchly to other columnists and film festival directors.
Administrative History
While living in Hollywood, California in the early 1970s, Rick Mechtly discover Vito Russo's column in the New York gay newspaper, GAY. Enthralled by Russo's pithy remarks, Mechtly started to assemble a collection of LGBT film related articles, columns, and reviews. Soon after GAY folded, Russo began touring the country with his lecture and film clip presentation, Celluloid Closet. With no other contact information, Mechtly decided to write to Jack Nichols, editor of GAY, in hopes of him forwarding a letter to Russo. It worked, Russo contacted him in 1978 and they briefly chatted about Mechtlys preservation of Russos columns. Russo insisted that Mechtly had the beginnings of a collection and suggested he make himself the communitys clipper of such materials. For more obscure clippings, Russo put him in touch with Peter Lowry, founder of the New York City Gay Film Festival, and Brenda Webb, founder of the Chicago Gay Film Festival. In 1981, Russo suggested that Mechtly share some of his oldest clippings with Larry Horne. Horne and others at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) were planning the first Los Angeles International Gay Lesbian Film Video Festival, which later became known as Outfest. After exchanging letters about once a year, in 1987 Mechtly and Horne were finally able to meet at the festival. In early 1988, Mechtly contacted Russo, inquiring about his inspiration for gay film writing. As he suspected, Russo was greatly influenced by Jack Babuscio, a writer for Londons Gay Times. Mechtly offered to collect the (recently deceased) Babuscios columns, in their entirety, for Russo. Of the nearly ninety columns, Mechtly already possessed three dozen. From there, he sought help from ONE National Gay Lesbian Archives, where another three dozen columns were uncovered. And at the recommendation of Horne, he contacted Stephen Bourne from the British Film Institute in London. Bourne assisted Mechtly in recovering the remaining columns. Upon receiving this gift, Russo called Mechtly to express his gratitude for the Babuscio collection.
Edited from Rick Mechley's text by Stacy Syroka
Access
The collection is open to researchers. There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deed of gift dated, December 15, 2012.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in the following series:
Series 1. Columns and correspondence
Series 2. Clippings
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection consists of articles, columns, and reviews regarding LGBT actors, motion pictures, and film festivals. Mechtly culled clippings from a variety of mainstream and LBGT magazines and newspapers, 1966-2011. The clippings includes Jack Babuscio's column, Screen Gays, Stephen Bourne's articles and columns, and many others. To a lesser extent the collection contains correspondence from Bourne and others to Mechtly.
Babuscio, Jack, 1937-1990; clippings files; Gays in motion pictures.; Lesbians in motion pictures
- Columns and correspondence, 1975-1999
  Scope and content
  The series includes clippings, correspondence, and filmographies. The clippings include columns written by Jack Babuscio, Stephen Bourne, and to a lesser extent Vito Russo. Correspondence files include Stephen Bourne letters to Mechtly along with a very limited number of other motion picture and/or film festival related correspondence. The series also includes several filmographies created by Frank Swilling and Rick Mechtly.
  Arrangement
  The folders were arranged alphabetically by the last name of their creators.
  - Jack Babuscio column Screen Gays, 1975-1982, 1990; [3 folders] (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
  - Jack Babuscio and Vito Russo columns, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Stephen Bourne columns, 1987-1994 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Stephen Bourne correspondence, 1992-1999 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Mechtly correspondence, 1982-1996; [3 folders] (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Mechtly filmographies, 1980, 1990; [2 folders] (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
  - Frank Swilling filmographies, 1989, 1995; [2 folders] (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
- Clippings, 1966-2011
  The series has been arranged chronologically. Some folders span multiple years which reflects Mechtly's original arrangement.
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of the collection consists of articles, columns, and reviews regarding LGBT actors, motion pictures, and film festivals. Mechtly culled clippings from a variety of mainstream and LBGT magazines and newspapers, 1966-2011. The bulk of the Vito Russo's writings are located in this series.
  The folders are arranged chronologically. Folders spanning multiple years reflect Mechtly's original arrangement.
  - 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1966-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1982, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1990, [3 folders] (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1993, [2 folders] (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - 1994, [3 folders] (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1995, [3 folders] (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1996, [3 folders] (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - 1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 2002, [2 folders] (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 2004, [2 folders] (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - 2005, [2 folders] (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
  - 2006, [2 folders] (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - 2007 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 2008 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - 2009 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - 2010 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - 2011 (Box 3, Folder 19)